<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sharp arrovv darted against the anabaptists, &amp;c. being an apology, or defence of the visible church upon Earth, and an objection to all such persons as doe rebaptize men and women, and against being covered at the divine exercise of preaching the word of God to the people, as also against those that deny to say the Lords Prayer / David Edmonds.</title>
            <author>Edmonds, David, fl. 1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08981</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E177B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R233358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61296973</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61296973</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180536</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08981)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2833:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sharp arrovv darted against the anabaptists, &amp;c. being an apology, or defence of the visible church upon Earth, and an objection to all such persons as doe rebaptize men and women, and against being covered at the divine exercise of preaching the word of God to the people, as also against those that deny to say the Lords Prayer / David Edmonds.</title>
                  <author>Edmonds, David, fl. 1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.H.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180536:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180536:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHARP ARROVV <hi>Darted against</hi> THE Anabaptiſts, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Being an Apology, or Defence of the Viſible Church upon Earth.</p>
            <p>And an Objection to all ſuch Perſons as doe Rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Men and Women.</p>
            <p>And againſt being covered at the Divine Exerciſe of Preaching the Word of God to the People.</p>
            <p>As alſo againſt thoſe that deny to ſay the Lords Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY DAVID EDMONDS,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>Prove all things: hold faſt that which is good,</q>
            <bibl>1. Theſ. 5. 21.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. H.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:180536:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180536:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Lady <hi>Anne Beauchamp,</hi> and to the Right Worſhipfull <hi>William Lewis,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onourable Lady, and moſt Noble Eſquire, Hee that had not a Lambe to bring to the Altar, there was a Turtle Dove, or two yong Pigeons, well accepted of: though this weak and unworthy Labour of mine, bee not worthy to bee read by your Honours, yet I ſhall intreat you to read it, and accept of my good will in ſtead of perfect action: the Widowes mite, was as well accepted in Gods Treaſury, as the ſuperfluity of the Rich and Wealthy: and I ſhall intreat your Honours the ſooner to read it, in regard that it was penned in Priſon, my ſelfe, groaning under the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Cavaliers and Parliamentarians, and that in a high nature: withall I would they would agree as well in all other matters, though I ſhould periſh. Thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting your Honours in theſe tumultuous times, to the tuition of the Lord God of Hoſts, who is that great man of Warre, and his Name is Jehovah. I humbly take leave, craving pardon for this great preſumption, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The humbleſt of your Servants, David Edmonds.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180536:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180536:3"/>
            <head>A ſharp Arrow darted againſt Anabaptiſts, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the firſt place King David, although hee was a man after Gods owne heart, yet hee ſhould not build the Lords Temple, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was a bloud-ſhedder; yet the Lord permitted him to make a preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his ſonne Salomon; ſo many talents of gold, and ſo many talents of ſilver, to undergoe the great worke commanded of God. The work being finiſhed, you ſhall read Salomons Prayer: And Salomon ſtood before the Altar of the Lord, in the preſence of the Congregation of Iſrael, and did ſpread out his hands towards heaven, and ſayd; Lord God of Iſrael, there is no God like thee, in heaven above nor in the earth beneath, who keepeſt covenant and mercy with thy ſervants that walke before thee, with all their hearts; who haſt kept with thy ſervant David my father that thou promiſedſt him; thou ſpakeſt it with thy mouth and haſt fulfilled with thy hand, as it is to this day. I ſhall omit to write what followes in that Chapter, in regard Salomon, and his ſon Rehoboam fell off from the command of the Lord; for God did not promiſe the Kingdome unto David, but upon condition, of the ſanctity of his poſterity; ſaying, If thy children will keepe my ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and obſerve my lawes, that I ſhall learne them, their children alſo ſhall ſit upon thy ſeat for evermore. Will God dwel on earth? behold, heaven and the heaven of heavens cannot contain him: how much leſſe this houſe that I have built, ſayth Solomon, 1. King. 8. 22. yet have thou reſpect unto the prayers and the ſupplications which thy ſervants ſhall make unto thee in this place: and hearken thou unto the ſupplications of thy ſervants, and of thy people Iſrael, when they ſhall pray towards this place, and heare thou in heaven thy dwelling place, and when thou heareſt, forgive.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:180536:4"/>
            <p>To prove that it is more commodious unto the ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of men, to pray to the Lord in the full Congregation, then pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, to be by ones ſelfe, or with a few company.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe I were in the publique Church, and have, as I have great need, to aske forgiveneſſe of my ſinnes at the hands of my God, or to make my ſupplication to his Majeſty, for ſome neceſſaries, either ſpirituall graces, or temporall benefits that I ſtand in great need of, it may be it will be Gods pleaſure to heare another for me, and I for him, and through that reſpect, God to commiſerate the preſent condition of us all.</p>
            <p>For the anſwer of God to the laſt requeſt of Abraham concerning Sodome and Gomorrah, was, If there, ſayes God, bee ten righteous men within thoſe two Cities, I will not deſtroy it for ten ſake: yet let no man conjecture, that I by no meanes doe debar private pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for why, the word of God ſayes, pray continually. And againe ſayes, and Phineas prayed, and ſo the plague ceaſed: for prayer is the very Key that opens heaven gate: nay withall it is ſuch a dart, the more a man or a woman doth uſe it, it further drives the Divel off from them; ſo is preaching neceſſary withall, as wee have an old Proverbe in the Welſh, Good is the ſtaffe with the crouch; they ſhould like man and wife goe hand in hand together, rather then to be ſeparated one from the other.</p>
            <p>Now to prove the Church to bee honoured before any other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate place, according as the New Teſtament doth deſcribe it, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde that our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, not in all the New Teſtament, that he did eat but naturall food, like other children, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he was twelve yeers of age; then his father and his mother found him in the Temple, in the midſt of the Doctors, hearing them, and asking of them queſtions. Aſſuredly if the Church were not to bee honoured before any other private place, our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt would aſwell begun the good action or the great meſſage of his Father in private places, aſſoone as the Church: but it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſeene, hee began it in the Temple, ſaying unto his Mother; Knew ye not that I muſt goe about my Fathers buſineſſe?</p>
            <p>Some men of the world will tell mee, that our Lord and Saviour Preached upon the Mount, and I doe in no wiſe contradict them, for the word ſayes ſo likewiſe: but when did hee preach upon the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180536:4"/> mountaine, but the time that he durſt not come into the Temple? for a while before did the Jewes hurle ſtones at him, that his ſacred perſon was driven to flie out of the Temple.</p>
            <p>Againe, to prove that the Church is to be honoured before any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther private place; if our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt had come up ſtreet or downe ſtreet, and there to ſee folkes ſell away Doves, our Lord and Saviour would have ſayd no kind of thing unto them, but let them attend their market in the name of God; but aſſoon as he eſpied them to ſell away Doves in the Temple, he ſcourged them out, and told them, that his Houſe was called the Houſe of Prayer, and that they had made it a den of theeves.</p>
            <p>Then thirdly, to prove it to bee more vertuous then private pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> read but 1. Cor. 11. 22. there the Apoſtle ſayes, have yee not houſes to eat and to drink in, why deſpiſe yee then the Church of God? will you have mee to prayſe you for this? I ſay unto you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I prayſe you not. And in the laſt of the Coloſſians the ſame Apoſtle ſayes, Let this Epiſtle be read in all the Churches of the Laodiceans.</p>
            <p>And to prove the Church to be honored before any private place, if a man can beleeve hiſtoricall writings; Titus Veſpaſian that great Emperour, forty yeeres after the crucifying of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, did race the Temple at Jeruſalem; and at the racing of it, when hee came to one Room there, called <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> the Holy of Holies, where none but the Prieſt once a yeere did enter into, he fell flat upon his face, and ſayd, This place could not chuſe otherwiſe to be, then the place where the moſt high God did dwell.</p>
            <p>If any other doe thinke to make it appeare unto me, that private places are as vertuous, let them proceed: for that choſen veſſel Saint Paul ſayes, He that is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill: I know they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove it by Scripture, which is the glaſſe of Gods will, and the very pathway to ſalvation, and the direct way which the ſonnes of men ought to teach, preach, and walk by. For further ſatisfaction to tender conſciences, I refer my ſelfe to the Learned to deſcribe it. Provided alwayes, that ſuch Learned men doe deteſt Popery on the one ſide, and ſhun Hereſie on the other ſide: for there be abundance of people in this age, did pretend to avoyd Popery, and fell into the gulfe of Hereſie; ſo that it may be well ſayd of ſuch people, with the words of the Poet, <hi>Incidit in Sillam qui vult vitare Charybdim.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180536:5"/> I doe not gaineſay but that there is a private Church withall to bee allowed of: for S. Paul writes, Coloſſ. 4. 15. Salute the Brethren which are in Laodicea, and to Nymphas and the Church which is in his houſe. So that private ſerving of God is neceſſary, but not ſo commodious as the publick ſervice in the Congregation; for in the time of that divine exerciſe, we ſhould all repair thither, to pray for our ſelves, and one for another, and God for us all. For we read of that godly woman Sarah, that ſhe did wear all her beſt aray, and did put on all her rich jewels, when ſhe did goe to worſhip the Lord in the Tabernacle. Was it the pride of Sarah that made her ſo to doe? no, no it was to grace and beautifie the Lords houſe: ſhe was pure within, and clean without: I would women in this age would imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of her wayes and actions, if they could not performe the whole.</p>
            <p>Now I will proceed to treat of the neceſſity of Baptizing of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, and the unlawfulnes of Rebaptizing of men or women either. Some men in this Country I heare there be, that ſay, that Baptiſme is not requiſite at all. I anſwer ſuch men: That if our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt were to be obliged unto mortall men, that hee is more bound unto the very Turke, then to ſuch perſons as doe deny Baptiſme: for why the Turk himſelfe doth acknowledge that there was failings in his Prophet Mahomet, his great head; and that there was no failings in that Prophet Jeſus Chriſt, as hee tearms him. If Baptiſme be not neceſſary, there were failings in Chriſt: for why? becauſe he ſuffered himſelfe to be Baptized of Iohn in Iordan. That is not only to ſhew the neceſſity of Baptiſme, but the obedience of Baptiſme alſo.</p>
            <p>But concerning the Rebaptizing of perſons, I ſhall confute ſuch men as hold it neceſſary, in the ſelf ſame Chapter as they themſelves doe ground it upon to be needfull or lawfull, or elſe I will bee ſure to confute them with the words of the ſame Apoſtle they ground it lawfull on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the words out of the Apoſtle that ſay, 19. of the Acts and the 2. verſe: Have ye received the Holy Ghoſt ſince ye beleeved, and they ſaid unto him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we have not heard ſo much whether there be any H. Ghoſt or no: and he ſaid unto them, unto what were ye then Baptized? and they ſaid, Unto Johns Baptiſme: then ſaid Paul, John verilie Baptized with the Baptiſme of Repentance, ſaying unto the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180536:5"/> People that they ſhould believe on him which ſhould come after him, that is one Jeſus Chriſt: when that they heard this they were Baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus: And when Paul had laid his hands on them, the Holy Ghoſt deſcended on them, and they ſpake with Tongues, and Propheſied, and all their men were about twelve in number.</p>
            <p>Let all true profeſſed Chriſtians but marke the falſe ground of Anabaptiſme; Johns Baptiſme, was, but as it were a Type of the Baptiſme of Jeſus Chriſt, for marke the words of the Apoſtle, in the fourth verſe of the ſame Chapter, that Johns Baptiſme was the Baptiſme of Repentance onely, and that they ſhould believe on him which ſhould come after him, that is, on Ieſus Chriſt, in whom is the fulneſſe of the God-head bodily, and the fulneſſe of Gods Spirit, and the fulneſſe of Baptiſme through Gods Spirit, and the fulneſſe of Grace, and the fulneſſe of all ſpirituall goodneſſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; ſo that the then Baptiſme of John, which was the Baptiſme of Repentance, and no more, and the now Baptiſme of Jeſus Chriſt, was, or is like two wayes upon a Hill, and at the foot of the Hill meete into one: ſo that the then Baptiſme of Iohn is as it were diſſolved, and now included into the Baptiſme of Ieſus Chriſt, which is altogether perfect and ſufficient: And therefore not to be wrought upon the Sonnes and Daughters of men, but at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time, or few dayes after that Children be borne into the World, as before the number that were Baptized of Paul after they were formerly Baptized with the Baptiſme of Repentance, as the Text ſayes were about twelve in number.</p>
            <p>And preſently as ſoone as Paul had layd his hands on them the Holy Ghoſt deſcended on them, and they ſpake all manner of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, and withall propheſied. I wonder whether theſe yong Schiſmaticall Gameſters at Lanhazan, or elſewhere, in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, can doe the like: I believe their Leaders, Mr. DAVIS and Mr. MILES can ſcarce do it; 'tis great pitty but that the Noble Eſtates of the Land, to the intent that the ſoules of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould not be enſnared and deluded in this kinde any further, ſhould be made acquainted of ſo great an abuſe to Church, State, and Commonwealth: For if the Eſtates did allow of it, they would ſend a Command for all to doe it in generall, thorow out the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180536:6"/> whole Land; therefore theſe abuſes are acted unknown unto them. Circumciſion as a type of Baptiſme, S. Paul in the 7. Cor. verſe 18. ſayes, Is any called being Circumciſed, let him not become Uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed: as much as if the Apoſtle had ſayd, Is any Baptiſed, let him not ſeeke to be Rebaptiſed: for if a man or woman doe ſuffer themſelves to bee Rebaptiſed, they doe deny the Baptiſme which they formerly received, and the firſt principles of the true Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Marke the words of the Apoſtle, 1. Cor. 7. 20. Let every man, ſayes he, abide in the ſame calling wherein hee was called; ſo that men or women being called by their firſt Baptiſme, as they are to be Chriſtians, and incorporated to be members of Gods true Church they ſhould ſo remayn, until their ſouls were diſſolved from their bodies, and their bodies from their ſoules, onely by vertue of the words of the Apoſtle in the ſayd 20. verſe as before, Let every man abide in the ſame calling wherein he was called.</p>
            <p>Unleſſe the ſonnes and daughters of men will altogether follow the falſe doctrine of theſe yong Seducers, and make fruſtrate the words of that choſen veſſell S. Paul, that wrote the very marrow of all the New Teſtament, the words of our Saviour only excepted.</p>
            <p>The Anabaptiſts, it may bee, will alleadge to mee, that a Childe ought not to be Baptiſed until he be of age, and poſſeſſed with faith: Alas, poore men! I anſwer them thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That as ſoone as the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife doth receive the Childe into the World, that very inſtant the Childe hath faith: what faith hath he? the faith that the father and mother that begat him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> have or had.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I did write ſo much of Circumciſion to bee a type of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, I know ſome particular men will alleadge and urge unto me the 1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. that Circumciſion is nothing, and Uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is nothing but the keeping of the Commandements: Tis true, every thing in the old Morall Law was aboliſhed at Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; but the Apoſtle doth not ſay Baptiſing is nothing; but hee might well enough ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Rebaptiſing is nothing; though wee were abſolved from the curſe of the Law at the comming of Chriſt, yet we are ſtill bound to the obedience of the Law, and the Law ſtands ſtill as a Schoolemaſter to bring us to Chriſt: for our Saviour ſayth in one place, I came not to deſtroy the Law or the Prophets, I came
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180536:6"/> rather to fulfill them.</p>
            <p>Though other Ceremonies were aboliſhed at the comming of Chriſt, yet Circumciſion was not quite aboliſhed then: why? Chriſt himſelfe was Circumciſed the eight day, it might bee aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed after; for our Saviour tooke no Celeſtiall Diſcipline upon him untill he was twelve yeers of age, poſing of the Doctors in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: yea then was Circumciſion aboliſhed, and Baptiſme to ſtand in the ſtead of it ever after.</p>
            <p>See in what a dangerous condition thoſe people are, that leave their Children Unbaptiſed untill they be of age: let them read Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus 4. 24. how that the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes becauſe he left his Childe ſo long a time Uncircumciſed: And it came to paſſe by the way, in the Inne, that the Lord met him and ſought to kill him, verſe 24.</p>
            <p>Then Zipporah took a ſharpe ſtone, and did cut off the foreskin of her ſon, and ſayd, ſurely a bloudy husband thou art unto me, v. 25.</p>
            <p>And ſhe ſayd againe, a bloudy husband thou art to mee, becauſe of the Circumciſion, verſe 26.</p>
            <p>Concerning the performance of our firſt Baptiſme, wee are in a dangerous condition, unleſſe God will look more upon the wounds of his dear ſon Jeſus Chriſt, then any merits of our owne. For men and women at our Baptiſme have entred into a Covenant to God for us, that we ſhould be ſuch and ſuch, and we for the moſt part of us, are ſuch and ſuch, cleane contrary to this Covenant, ſo that if we will ſeriouſly conſider, we have enough to doe to performe the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of our firſt Baptiſme, without provoking the Lord to anger to take upon us the ſecond Baptiſme, which is clean contrary to the word of God. But it is nothing in this age, with the ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to abridge Covenants, ſeldome or never at all doe they think upon them.</p>
            <p>Concerning the breach of this Covenant, I have read in Hiſtory, that Vladiſlaus King of Hungaria, and Prince of Tranſylvania, how he waged war with the Great Turk, and in proceſſe of time being weary on both ſides waging of warre, both parties agreed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the differences betwixt them to a peace; the King of Hungaria being a Chriſtian, the Turk a Mahometan: they both entred into a ſolemne Oath and Covenant, to diſſolve both Armies, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180536:7"/> a League between them for ſo many yeeres; the King of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia took his Oath in Chriſt his Name, the Turk in Mahemets: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that both Armies were diſſolved, and every man went home to his owne houſe in peace. A while after, Julian the Cardinall, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary, (even as incendiaries have fomented theſe unnatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all warres in this Land) perſwades the King of Hungaria to abridge this Covenant, and againe to riſe up in Armes againſt the Turk, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the King of Hungaria that it was no ſin againſt God to breake that Covenant with the Turk, becauſe he was a Pagan; ſo hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with the King of Hungaria that he roſe up in Armes preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: ſo the Turk in defence of his Territories and Kingdomes, roſe up in Armes withall; and in the Brunt and heat of the Warre, the Turk eſpying the Crucifix in the Banner of the King of Hungaria, takes the Covenant out of his Pocket, and throwes it up towards Heaven, and ſayes, O Chriſt, if thou beeſt the Living God, revenge not thy ſelfe upon me, for I never took any Covenant in thy Name, for I did alwayes deny thee to be an Eternall God; but revenge thy ſelfe upon the King of Hungaria, that hath taken a Covenant in thy Name, and is not aſhamed before thy face to break it.</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly, our not performing of the Covenant of our firſt Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, Covenant of our Mariages, and other ties that wee have taken upon us in this Land, tis to be feared that by reaſon wee have ſo oft times abridged them, that Turks, Pagans, and Infidels, will riſe up in judgement againſt us.</p>
            <p>In part of this weak and unworthy Labour of mine, as far as God hath given me a talent, I ſhall declare unto the World the unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of being covered in the Church, at the Divine exerciſe of Preaching the word of God to the people.</p>
            <p>I will begin with the words of God himſelfe Exod. 13. 5. Plucke off thy ſhooes from of thy feet, for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt is holy ground: by vertue of thoſe words, the words of the moſt High God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I tell, O proud Belteſhazzar, plucke off thy Hat from of thy head, for the words thou heareſt are holy words. <hi>I</hi> doe not ſay but an old man may doe it, or a ſick man may bee covered at that Divine exerciſe, for tis a caſe of neceſſity; for King David did eat the Shew-bread, that was not lawfull for any to eat, but the Prieſt alone: God never ſent any Prophet to reprehend him for it: why?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180536:7"/> becauſe David was neceſſitated ſo to doe at that time; but as ſoone as he took the wife of Uriah, the Lord preſently ſent the Prophet Nathan to attaint him of High Treaſon, againſt the great God of Heaven and Earth, and to judge and condemne him in one word, Thou art the man.</p>
            <p>There were fifty thouſand of the Bethſhemites ſlaine for looking unreverently upon the Ark of the Covenant; and Uzzah was ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken dead by the hand of the Lord, for but touching the Ark, as you may read Chron. 13. 9. 10. And when they came to the threſhing floor of Chidon, Uzzah put forth his hand to hold the Arke, for the Oxen ſtumbled. And the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt Uzzah, and he ſmote him becauſe hee put his hand to the Arke, and there he died before God.</p>
            <p>The Preacher is the Ark of the Covenant of the New Teſtament, and when hee preaches unto us of Gods judgements, wee ſhould then pray in our hearts to divert thoſe judgements from us; and when he treats and ſpeaks of Gods mercies, we ſhould then pray in our hearts to participate of thoſe mercies: you ſhall finde it in one place that S. Paul writes, that it is a ſhame for a woman to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in the Church; as much as if the ſame Apoſtle had ſayd, that it is a ſhame for a man to be covered in the Church: therefore I beſeech all thoſe that love God, and the true Reformation of the Church of God, to reform this enormous abuſe, leſt wee ſhould any further be evill ſpoken of and derided by Turks, Papiſts, Pagans, and Infidels, that are not enſpired to make recognition of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; leſt that their blind wayes ſhould at the laſt day riſe up in judgement againſt us; for aſſuredly unleſſe that this and other abuſes that are now committed in the Church of God bee amended, we ſhall be in great danger to bee thoſe, (or like thoſe) that the Apoſtle Peter writes of, 1. Pet. 5. the two laſt verſes, It had beene better for you never to have known the way of truth, then to know it and turne from it. For ye ſhall bee like a dog that turns againe to his owne vomit, or like a ſow that is waſhed in the River, and goes wallowing againe in the mire.</p>
            <p>I can in no wiſe bridle my tongue from ſpeaking, nor with-hold my hand from writing of the wrongs that are now done unto cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180536:8"/> Clergy men, that taught and preached the Goſpel in prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent times; yet let no man conjecture that I by no meanes doe write of their ſides in generall; for I know, abundance of them would not bee contented to walke upon the Battlements of the Church, but did mount themſelves up to the turrets of civill policy that did nothing belong unto them.</p>
            <p>Some of them have been reſponſall for it before men already, and ſuffered, and therefore I ſhall conclude of ſuch perſons with the old Proverb, which ſayes, <hi>de mortibus nil niſi bonum;</hi> of the dead no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but good. I take God to Reco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, my Lord Generall CROM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVELL, as his Excellency was going for Ireland, upon the walls of Tenbigh, told the Gentlemen there about him, I cannot perceive (ſayes he) but this man is of the ſelfe ſame Religion as my ſelfe is of; meaning my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>For my owne part, I shall ſooth no man, be he ever ſo great; if his Excellency do agree to extirpe out of the Vineyard all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in times paſt, his Excellency is as wide from my tenents in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, but methinks as many of them ſhould be thruſt out of the Vineyard, as had evill will at Sion, and none of the reſt: for to put them all out, we have no ſuch warant, neither out of the Old nor the New Teſtament; for in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament we read, that in the laſt requeſt of Abraham to God, for Sodome and Gomorrah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if there (ſayes God) be ten righteous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in thoſe two Cities, I will not deſtroy it for the tens ſake: But there was found there but one righteous Lot, and for that one righteous man, God had provided a Zoar a City of refuge, during the time that the Lords anger was kindled againſt thoſe two great Cities in deſtroying of them with fire and Brimſtone from his Celeſtiall habitation: And now it ſhould ſeeme that in a ſmall meaſure his Majeſty is offended with certaine men that he called to be his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and eſpeciall Members of his Church; but it cannot be that all the Clergy in times paſt could be culpable of adhering to Popery or the like, and in this fire from Heaven, which is the Lords ſmall anger, or his ſmall deluge emerging the former Clergy men; if there (I ſay) be but one amongſt them, that can ſay and prove him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not guilty, where is his Zoar, or any City of refuge.</p>
            <p>Elias a great Prophet and a choſen of the Lord, deſired of the Lord,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180536:8"/> that he might be taken away from amongſt the children of men, ſaying, they have killed thy Prophets, &amp;c. and I onely am left, and they ſeeke my life alſo: in anſwer to Elias, God ſaies, I have reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſeven thouſand choſen men in Iſraell, that have not bended their knees to Baal.</p>
            <p>It ſhould ſeeme by thoſe words though Eliah had the inſpiration of Gods ſpirit in him, in a high nature, yet hee did not know the mentall reſervations of all men and women towards their God in Iſrael. And ſo according to morall reaſon, that the noble Eſtates of the Land doe not know of every particular wrong that is now done to ſome of the former Clergy men; every veſſell ſhould ſtand upon its owne bottome: why? becauſe there is ſo much Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, muſt there be no wine nor ſtrong drink? and becauſe there is ſo much Leachery, muſt there be no women? God forbid. Now I prove that thoſe Clergy men heeretofore, that had not a hand to bring in Popery into the Church of God, neither did in no wiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to quench or put out the light of the Goſpel, but behaved themſelves reverently, and prudently in their vocations, ought not to be put out of their Benefices: nay if they had committed ſome faults, yet they ought not to bee put and thruſt out of the Vineyard in this kind, for one particular fault: for why? let ſome of the ſons and daughters of men but think with themſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat if God in the dreadfull day of judgement, ſhould deale with us as we deale heere below one with another, what would become of us? aſſuredly wee ſhould goe on the left hand with the Goats<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Goe ye curſed &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Concerning the remiſſion that many of the former Clergy men ſhould have to prove it. We read that our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt when he came into the Vineyard, and there found a Tree that bare no fruit, he bad the Vineyard dreſſer cut it down, why cumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it the ground? Nay ſayes the Vineyard dreſſer, I will entrench and dig about it one yeer more: wee doe not read that our Saviour did contradict the Vineyeard dreſſer in that buſines</p>
            <p>For one particular man a Clergy man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> one Mr. FRANCIS DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIES of Llangaine, in the County of Glamorgane in Wales a man that would never hear of Mariage his reaſon was, leſt the care of a wife and children ſhould in part take him off from the ſervice of his God, and the duty that hee was to performe to the great charge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180536:9"/> him: then his ſecond reaſon was, if he ſhould mary, hee could not be a ſupporter to many of his friends, which he was to divers of them: nay he took more pains in his Calling to Preach the word of God in his two Pariſhes, then any two Clergy men in the County of Glamorgan: and for this man to bee thruſt out of his Benefices, and ſtill to be kept from them, tis great pity indeed: for the reſt of the former Clergy of the County of Glamorgan, they be of age, let them ſpeak for themſelves.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have made the fourth part of this weake and unworthy work which I have already penned, that is, concerning the Lords Prayer, and againſt ſuch perſons as doe deny the ſaying of it: loath I was to make deſcription of it, in regard that it is, as it were, the maſter piece of Chriſt Jeſus his own words, leſt that God ſhould be ſo offended with me, as he did ſtrike Uzzah for touching the Ark of the Covenant. But upon a Sabbath day being the 19. of Sept. 1651. to heare one Mr. ELLIS make an Expoſition on part of the Lords Prayer, in the Church of Cardiffe, the words thus: Hallowed bee thy Name, thy Kingdome come, thy will be done in Earth as it is in Heaven: where he ſayd, that people did tempt God to ſay the Lords Prayer: why ſayd he? becauſe the Angels and Saints in Heaven do pray and ſerve God perfect, and we unperfect: that is moſt true: but I hold his and others coverture and debarment in it to bee to think it as it were a certaine imbecillity or weakneſſe in our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, to command his Apoſtles to ſay it, and that we ſhould not imitate them to ſay it likewiſe. Doth he or any other of the ſons of men thinke that our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt when he ſaid, thy will be done in earth as it is in heaven, did meane that mortall men, that are conceived and borne in ſinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all their dayes live in ſinne, and altogether polluted with corruption and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, can execute the good will of the Father as well as thoſe celeſtiall Saints and Seraphins that do dayly and hourely reape the fruition of the heavenly Deity, and habituall ſociety with Almighty God? no, no, the meaning of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, was, that the ſons and daughters of men ſhould doe their beſt endeavour to execute his will and pleaſure upon earth, and that which they ſhould be defective in, the reſt ſhould be ſupplyed out of his bleſſed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180536:9"/> merits; for Zacharias and Elizabeth were ſaid to walke in all the Commandements of the Lord; no queſtion but they both one time or other had abridged the Lords Commandements, but ſuch lapſes were not attributed unto them: why? becauſe they did their beſt endeavour to execute the will of their God; for God requires no more at our hands, but to do our beſt to ſerve him in uprightneſſe of hearts and willingneſſe of ſpirits, and the defects as be, are to be ſupplyed out of the bleſſed merits of Jeſus Chriſt: and withall, I ſhall conclude this ſentence with the words of that ſweet ſinger of Iſrael, David the King; he knoweth whereof we are made, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth we are but duſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the both Evangeliſts do not concurre or agree in the writing of the Lords prayer; the one hath it, when ye pray, pray ye thus, <hi>verbatim,</hi> word by word: the other hath it, when ye pray, pray ye as thus: and in theſe times thoſe that debarre it, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe neither: for why? we ſhould either ſay it word by word, as the one hath it, or elſe take it as a modell, or as it were a Text to pray by it; for aſſuredly, our Saviour did not ſpeake it vainely, but that either of the both ſhould be followed in it: nay, he much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the vaine babblings and long prayers of the Scribes and Phariſees, and comprehended the prayers of his ſervants in this ſhort prayer, Our Father, &amp;c. and did compoſe it to ſix Petitions; the firſt three for the glory of God, the other three for the neceſſity of man; and the beſt Divine in this Land may preach a whole twelvemonth, twiſe every Sabbath day, and perhaps not conſumate or end all the Doctrine of this good and godly Prayer.</p>
            <p>I could have made this Booke three times as long, but as far as I am called to be a Chriſtian, though a great ſinner, I hope I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared my ſelfe to God and the world of and concerning the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of my tenents in Religion, in theſe foure things, and whoſo will queſtion me for it. for I ſhall think my ſelfe happy to ſacrifice my bloud in the quarrell of my Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, that ſpared not his ſacred hearts bloud for my redemption from the thraldome of Satan, that old enemy of mankinde, that ſtill goeth about the world like a roaring Lion, ſeeking whom hee may devour. Great bloudſhedding (the more the pitty) hath beene in this Land, of, and concerning ſuch differences, as are now between
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180536:10"/> Mr. ELLIS and my ſelfe: Counſell what we may, fight about it as long as we pleaſe, we are all proclaimed in the word of God to be unprofitable ſervants, the proudeſt of us all: and it will be one day ſaid unto us, give account of your Stewardſhips, you ſhall be no longer Stewards; who ſhall end this controverſie, between Mr. ELLIS and my ſelfe? ſhall the Commiſſioners of Array end it? no, I challenge them, for they did impriſon me for nineteen weekes and foure dayes in Cardiffes Goale for my affection to the noble Parliament and the Army, and gave away my meanes, 100l. <hi>per annum</hi> to one Major WINSOR, a ranke Papiſt: ſhall the Gentlemen that beare the rule, and the ſway now in the County of Glamorgan end it? no, I challenge ſome of them likewiſe: for they did me greater wrongs then the Commiſſioners of Array have done me formerly: but for my owne part, I ſhall reſt my ſelfe contented about ſuch injuries, untill my Redeemer comes in the aire, in the very Clouds themſelves, to judge both quick and dead, and then if I ſhall not obtaine mercy at the ſweet hands of my Saviour, I ſhall be ſure to have juſtice adminiſtred to this my tired ſoule upon earth; I have had neither of them both here below, I am ſure of it.</p>
            <p>Then there will be no Biſhop favouring Popery, no Mechanicke Tradeſman preaching Hereſie, no Lawyer pleading, nor no Attorny prating, for the diſſolution of the vaſt world, and all that is therein, wilbe like the unrowling of an Exchequer Writ: when that it is fully opened it roules it ſelfe up againe, and the Judiciary Sentence is ready for us all. Come ye Bleſſed, and go ye curſed; yea, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py will that ſervant be, when that his Maſter commeth, he ſhall finde to be watchfull; for he ſhall receive that comfortable Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, <hi>Euge bone ſerve,</hi> well done good and faithfull ſervant, thou haſt been faithfull in a little, be thou ruler over much: enter thou into thy Maſters joy: To the which joy of our Lord and Maſter Ieſus Chriſt, make us all to be partakers; To whom, as is moſt meet, be aſcribed all Honour, Glory, Might, Majeſty, Dominion, and Thankſgiving, both now and for evermore, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:180536:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
